<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Poomalairaj's weblog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2012-04-17T19:52:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>N900 not booting</title><link href="/n900-not-booting.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-04-17T19:52:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Poomalairaj</name></author><id>tag:,2012-04-17:n900-not-booting.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;N900 not booting : I almost bricked my phone. No initfs \o/&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I messed with easy debian chroot on my N900 so, I deleted the easy debian image and copied fresh one to my N900. When I was trying to install phpmyadmin in easydebian, suddenly N900 turned off and then rebooted. It was stuck at showing five dots animation splash screen foreaver and never loads desktop. I tried to reboot, remove battery and inserted again. Still my N900 not booting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="N900 Booting" src="/static/img/n900-booting.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a last resort, I tried to flash N900. Flashing went well but still the problem was there. I thought I bricked my N900. My wife will kill me if I ask another N900. :(&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I found cpitchford’s notes on nokia forum. He hinted to turn on R&amp;amp;D mode of N900.
So I did the following…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Enable R&amp;amp;D mode in N900&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch off the phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press and hold “U” button on the keyboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;insert usb cable on N900 and insert other end to PC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let go the “U” key once you see Nokia logo and USB icon on the top right corner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now open a commnad prompt and enter following command to turn on the R&amp;amp;D mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo flasher-3.5 --enable-rd-mode&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once the flasher completes that, remove usb cable and reboot the phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cpitchford’s said it should boot now. But mine didn’t. But it provided me an important information. It said &lt;strong&gt;No initfs \o/&lt;/strong&gt; while turning on the phone. So it seems initfs is missing on the phone. The initfs actually resides in EMMC. Oh my god. If I flash EMMC, I will lose all my data… again…! :(&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay. There is no better option now. I have to flash EMMC. To do that I following steps from 1 to 4 and then entered the following commands&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;flasher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;3.5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;F&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;RX&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;51&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_2009SE_20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;.2010.36&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_PR_COMBINED_MR0_ARM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;flasher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;3.5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;F&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;RX&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;51&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_2009SE_10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;.2010.13&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;2.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;VANILLA_PR_EMMC_MR0_ARM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;First command flashes the OS and the second one flashes Emmc and create the lost initfs again. After the second command finish its job, the device will reboot.
Again the five dots animation… But wait… yay, My N900 boots normally and the mighty hildon desktop is loaded successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somebody said in forum that, &lt;strong&gt;There is no such thing as bricked N900 as long as there is not physical or component damage&lt;/strong&gt;. It is true. Again I have to install all the stuff again. sigh…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will update in another blog post about the settings I usually do after flashing N900.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="n900"></category></entry></feed>